<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blood of righteous Abel crying from the ground being a lamentation for and a warning too [sic] all that have a hand against the innocent people of God, especially intended for the rulers and priests in Hamshire ... / by W.B.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29028</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10793977</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10793977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45945</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1415:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blood of righteous Abel crying from the ground being a lamentation for and a warning too [sic] all that have a hand against the innocent people of God, especially intended for the rulers and priests in Hamshire ... / by W.B.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45945:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The blood of righteous ABEL, Crying from the ground, being a lamentation for, and a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning too, all that have a hand againſt the innocent people of God, eſpecially intended for the Rulers and Prieſts in <hi>Hamſhire,</hi> who have hardned their hearts againſt the day of ſlaughter, wherein they ſhall feel <hi>Cains</hi> puniſhment which he was not able to bear, who have been often warned by the ſervants of the Lord, yet have they not done that which is juſt in his ſight, but have impriſoned ſeveral of his ſervants this many months, without juſt cauſe, and doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their bondage upon us, where 9 of us are kept cloſe priſoners, in an unwholeſome ſtinking hoale, not fit for beaſts, whoſe cry is not onely gone through the Nation, but is alſo entred into the ears of the Lord God of reſt, who will plead our cauſe in righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Alſo the decree of the Lord ſealed and made manifeſt to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that all the plottings, ſnares and perſecutions, which the powers of the earth and darkneſs, and the gates of hell, can invent and riſe up with, ſhall never prevail againſt his power that is now brake forth and made manifeſt, in his dear children, who in ſcorne are called Quakers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>MY heart within me is broken becauſe of the falſe Prophets &amp; perſecuting ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, who are found fighting againſt the Lamb of God and his followers. Alas, alas! woe is me becauſe of the miſery that is coming upon you, my heart is filled with ſorrow, and mine eyes with tears, and my bowels are turned within me, to conſider the day of your deſolation and deſtruction, which is coming upon you, from the Almighty God of heaven and earth: Oh what ſhall be done for you, ye hard harted and rebellious children, who ſhall intreat for you, or take pitty on you in the day of your calamity, which is coming as a whirlwind of terrors, and you ſhall not eſcape, and woe be to him that ſtrive with his maker: do you think to ſtop or limit the mighty power of the Creator of heaven &amp; earth, which is now broke forth and made manifeſt in his dear children, (who have waited for him in the way of his judgements) by your blood thirſty perſecution; and by your falſe accuſations and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conſultations and unrighteous decrees and lawes, nay you ſhall never prevail nor proſper in theſe your intents, your vain hopes will periſh, and your contrivances will be ſwept with you into the bottomleſs pit, from whence your counſel is, and no weapon that is formed againſt us, (who love not our lives for the ſon of Gods ſake unto the death)
<pb facs="tcp:45945:2"/> ſhall ever proſper, and woe to the rebellious children that take counſel but not of me, and that cover with a covering, but not of my ſpirit ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Is your councels, plottings and perſecution to hinder the powerful work of the Lord, which he hath begun among the children of men, and hath bleſſed and will bleſs, and to frey people from embraceing the precious truth (which is the everlaſting foundation of God) without which all men will be found miſerable in their latter end, is this your end, and to keep up your earthly honour, deceit and flattering titles, and vain glory, which will wither and be laid in the duſt, and to ſatisfie the pride of life, which is not of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but of the world: Is this your end, for fear of loſeing theſe things that puffs up the fleſhly mind out of Gods fear, and that warrs againſt your ſouls, for which you perſecute, impriſon, and draw before the judgement ſeats, and make a prey and a ſpoyl of a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and innocent people, whoſe glory and kingdome, and peace is not of the world, but follows the lamb that was ſlain whither ſoever he goeth; if this be your end, (and to keep off the trouble and torment that is coming upon you, by reaſon of your wickedneſs and rebellion againſt the Lord) you will miſs of it, and your expectation will periſh, and do you think to avenge your ſelves on his dear children, and get eaſe by aflicting them, and grieving them, and tormenting them with your plottings and ſnares of inhumane cruelty, is this your way? is the time that was ſpoken of, come to be fulfilled upon you? that whoſever killeth us (who are the followers of Chriſt) ſhall think he doth God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and will not their vain thoughts deceive them, who are found in the envy againſt the meek ſpirit, that is come to judge the world, and do not they riſe up againſt the Lord of life; who riſe up againſt him that is meek and lowly: ſurely this is a wrong way you have entred into, the way of the ungodly which will periſh, and not the way to peace, for in theſe things you heap up wrath to your ſelves againſt the day of wrath, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the righteous judgements of God, in this way you ſhall never proſper nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, the Lord God hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>For this is the way of the wicked, which is as darkneſs (where the ſtumbling is) and leads into the chambers of death and deſtruction, this is the ſword of the wicked which you have drawn, it ſhall enter into your own bowels, and if you thirſt for our blood, you may have it to drink, for a body is prepared, and we fear not him that is able onely to kill it, but the Lord our God alone, he is our fear, and he is our dread, and our refuge in time of trouble, who is taking vengeance on you unawares, in a way you know not, nor will you believe though a man declare it unto you, for did you believe it, and were the eye open to ſee theſe things, you would fear and dread and tremble at the preſence of the pure powerful God, whoſe ſwift witneſs is coming upon you as a thief in the night, and will wound your hairy ſcalp, who proceed in your wickedneſs, and will ſmite the head of his enemies, and ſtrike through Kings in the day of his wrath, whoſe fury you cannot eſcape; and all your high mountains by him will be overturned, who think to rule and reign over the meek of the earth, by your hight of pride and cruelty: alas for you! ye tall Cedars, a fierce wind from the Lord God ſhall ſhake you, the axe is laid to your root, and you will be hewn down for the fire, ye raging waves of the ſea, you ſome out your own ſhame, and caſt up mire and dirt, our King (that rides meekly) is on the top of you all, and on your head doth he trample, and he will calm this ſtorme to his own praiſe and glory, and to your utter confuſion who rebel againſt him.</p>
            <p>Chriſt Jeſus the light of the world, the man of ſorrows, who ſeek not honour from men, whom you deſpiſe, againſt whom you are riſen up and have turned your ſword, he is our King, here this ye rebels, ye traytors, the Lord God will ſtain the pride of your glory, and lay your earthly honour in the duſt, and bring you into contempt, who are ſeeking honour and glory to your ſelves in the earth, whoſe peace is your life, who
<pb facs="tcp:45945:2"/> love the praiſe of men, and pleaſures more then God: a ſword is coming upon you all, and you are for the ſlaughter of the great King who is our lawgiver, and Saviour, and our peace, who is come a light into the world, and is the true light that lighteneth every man that cometh into the world, meek and lowely upon the wild aſſes coalt, hear this ye deaf, and ſee ye blind, and be ſtill and hearken, ye flouds of ungodly men who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Saints about and the beloved city, with lies and plottings of falſehood, whereby you think to weary out the dear children of the moſt high: fire is coming down from God out of heaven to devour you, and you ſhall not be able to quench it, ye are the pricking briars to the houſe of Iſrael, ye are the thorns, the droſs, and the ſtubble, the Lord God Almighty of power, will you conſume the decree is ſealed againſt you, a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I am for the eternal God of life againſt you all, in all your deeds of darkneſs, and hard ſpeeches; my outward life is not deer unto me, ye devouring beaſts of the field, I have given it up, and you may take it, for he that departeth from iniquity is become your prey.</p>
            <p>But the Lord God will plead our cauſe in righteouſneſs, and his eternal witneſs (the light in your conſciences) will anſwer your condemnation to be juſt, and your deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be of your ſelves; for you have been warned from time to time, by the ſervants of the Lord without you, and reproved by the light, his true prophet within you, that you might eſcape &amp; flee from the wrath to come, which if you proceed in the harneſs of your hearts, in afflicting his dear children, it will over take you: and becauſe of theſe things, my ſoul is moved, knowing the terrors of the Lord againſt you, and a doleful lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is on me, and my very bones are pained, and my heart is hot within me, the whole earth is moved with the fierce indignation of the Lord, his vengeance plagues, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal judgements (without mercy) do I proclaim againſt you all, from the mouth of the Lord God of hoſts, except you ſpeedily repent; for you have greived his ſpirit, and you have afflicted his dear children theſe many months, yet have you been intreated by them with many tears, and often warned, and the Lord have we even intreated for you, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did for <hi>Sodome,</hi> &amp; <hi>Moſes</hi> for <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that you might not wholly be condemned, with an utter overthrow, but rather that you might repent and live; but our righteous ſouls are vexed and grieved with your pride, rebellion, and filthy converſation from day to day, and no anſwer from the Lord have we concerning you, but the red ſea of his wrath wherein you will be utterly ſwallowed and drowned, and not one will be left, and fire from heaven as ſnares upon you, will be rained, for every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, ſhall be hewn down and caſt into the fire, and every plant which my heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father hath not planted ſhall be rooted up. Conſider this ye that forget God, ye that forget mercy, whoſe bowels are ſhut up, whoſe hearts are hardned, from his righteous dreadful fear, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you, for our God is a conſuming fire, and is terrible to the heathen that know him not, whoſe fire is in <hi>Sion,</hi> and his furnace in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and from thence our deliverer comes, who turns away un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs from <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is not envy, perſecution, and oppreſſion, ungodlineſs, and wrath, pride, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, are not theſe things ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs? conſider and weigh it in the even ballance the light in your conſciences, to which I ſpeak, which will anſwer the truth without covering, and is my witneſs in you all, for the Lord God, and heareth my voyce, therefore ſtop not the ear, leſt you are ſhut out for ever; then ſhall you cry but he will not hear you: and is not the wrath of God to be revealed from heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men, or is envy, pride, cruelty, oppreſſion, tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and perſecution, and laying ſnares for the innocent and harmeleſs without cauſe, is this good fruit, or the fruit of the ſpirit of God, (who among the ſaints in theſe things is your example,) or doth the heavenly plant bring forth ſuch fruit, nay verily will
<pb facs="tcp:45945:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Gods witneſs anſwer me, and are any the ſons and children of God, but who are joyned to the heavenly plant, or led by his ſpirit, which guides unto all truth, (out of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs) into ſoberneſs, quietneſs, love, peace, patience, long-ſuffering, humility, and gentleneſs, &amp;c. and are not the children of God in theſe things manifeſt? and are not the children of the divel, (in the other ground bringing forth other fruit of the curſe) alſo manifeſt? But if you will not hear, nor lay theſe things to heart, and give over afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, oppreſſing, and grieving my dear children, and tender babes that cry unto me night and day, and give glory to my great and dreaful name, by returning from the evil that is in your hands, I will deſtroy you and your ſeed from off the face of the whole earth, &amp; blot out your name from under heaven, and your remembrance ſhall ſtinck (and be a grief) to my choſen, yet ſhall they rejoyce over you, when the ſmoke of your torment ſhall aſcend up for ever and ever, ſaith the Lord God Almighty,</p>
            <p>For thus ſaith the Lord God, theſe people whom you hate (and ſeek many waies to enſnare and take counſel together againſt, and abuſe and perſecute, and impriſon, whip, ſtone, revile and reproch by the name <hi>QUAKERS,</hi> who abide faithful to my ſon the light of the world, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world; they are dear unto me, my choſen, my dear children, my beloved ones, and he that toucheth them, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the apple of mine eye, whoſe cry is entred into my ears, and my pitty is towards them, and my bowels are moved for them, for whoſe ſake I will reprove Kings, and kingdomes ſhall be overthrown that riſe up againſt them, and every tongue that riſe up in judgement againſt them, will I condemne, for I the Lord ſearch the heart, and try the reins, and will reward every man according to his deeds.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider theſe things, ye proud and ſcornful men, who are of the birth born after the fleſh, perſecuting the birth of the ſpirit, being moved with envy &amp; wrath (which is of the Divel) againſt an innocent people, whom the Lord God will preſerve and doth, though out of your ſight, whom the God of this world hath blinded, and all you falſe teachers, deceitful workers, who uſe your tongues both to pray and alſo to lye, flander, and revile; whoſe hearts are exerciſed in covetous practiſes, and yet ſometime (for a cloke) will ſpeak againſt it, as if one fountain can yield ſalt water and freſh, but your skirts are diſcovered upon your face, and you ſhall be made manifeſt to them that yet ſee you not, and ſhall be a by word to nations, ye proud prophane hirelings, ye trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> from you prophaneſs is gone forth into all the land, who by your lyes and by your lightneſs hath cauſed many to erre, the Lord God will root you out without hand, and the very ſavour of your root ſhall become loathſome to the earth, (which is weary to bare you) and your foundation ſhall be utterly ſwept away, and no place for it ſhall be found, for you have been founded upon (and upheld by) the beaſtly nature and ſeed of enmity, within and without, of which now the Lord God of endleſs ſtrength, is making an utter end, and none ſhall be able to deliver out of his hand, therefore is a cry heard among you, to the hills and to the mountains of the earth, to hide and cover you from the wrath of the lamb, againſt whom you make war, (who is the light of the world and your condemnation whoſe deeds are evil) but the mountains ſhall be overturned with the fierce indignation of the Lord, and caſt into the ſea of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and torment with you, who ſtrive to hide you from the day that makes manifeſt, and from the ſtroke of his righteous judgements, and the fury of the Lord God Almighty will ſweep the land of evil doers, and no place ſhall be found for the worker of iniquity, but ſhame and confuſion of faces ſhall come upon you, and you ſhall gnaw your tongues for pain, and ſhall curſe your God and your King, for a dreadful and bitter day is faſtning upon you all, who are in the enmity againſt the meek ſpirit (in <hi>Cains</hi> nature) va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond from God in the earth where your names are written, and not in the Lambs book of life that was ſlain from the foundation of the world, (the foundation of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion)
<pb facs="tcp:45945:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> when envy, and pride, and vain glory had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpirit was ſlain by it, hear this ye that have an ear to hear, for he ſhall reign and get the victory, that was dead and is alive for evermore, and hath the key of <hi>David,</hi> and ſhall overcome and have the dominion, and rule and authority over all the kingdomes of men: ô ye fooliſh and without underſtanding, I have ye not read, that the lamb that vvas ſlain is worthy to receive power, riches, wiſdom, ſtrength, honour, glory and bleſſing, and that he ſhall prevail though ten Kings make war with him; conſider this ye that ſtrive with your maker, by whom you will be broken in pieces like a potters veſſel, and was it not the Dragon (which is caſt out of heaven) that makes war with the lamb, and was it not the Divel which had great wrath, when he ſaw he had but a ſhort time, and was it not the great red Dragon, the old ſerpent, that made war with the woman, and the remnant of her ſeed, who kept the Commandements of God, and had the teſtimony of Jeſus, theſe are them, the divel, the ſerpent, and his ſeed makes war againſt, againſt them that keep the commands of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus, who ſaith believe in the light, and how can ye believe which receive honour one of another, and ſaith ſwear not at all, and they ſhall hale you out of their Sinagogues and bring you before ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and governours for my nameſake, and this ſhall turn to you for a teſtimony, <hi>(mark)</hi> for his ſake that ſaith, ſwear not at all for his nameſake, that reſpecteth not the perſon of any man, for his nameſake that ſaith, how can ye believe, that receive honour one of another, for his nameſake that teſtifie againſt the works of the world that are evil, haled out of the Synagogues, brought before rulers, perſecuted and deſpitefully uſed for his ſake, for keeping his commandements, and bearing his teſtimony againſt whom the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and his ſeed makes war, heer's the teſtimony, but the woman that brings forth the man child, (againſt whom the dragon caſt out his flouds of reproch and perſecution) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hid from the face of the ſerpent, glory to the Lord for ever.</p>
            <p>And is not the lamb, the light of the holy city, where the dogs that bite and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean devouring beaſts ſhall not enter, but are ſhut out, and all lyers, and unbelieving, who believe not in the light of the world, in the lamb of God that taketh away the ſin, whoſe Kingdome and glory is hid from the wiſe and prudent of the world, whoſe face to them is marred, and his forme more then the ſons of men, who know not the bride the lambs wife, for the glory of the kings daughter is within, and not of the viſible world, therefore the world knoweth her not, and the Princes of this world never knew the Lord of glory, who lighteth every man that cometh into the world: hearken ye bitter ſpirits, ye haſty, raſh, and high minded men, whoſe wrath and pride blinds your underſtandings that you cannot perceive the inviſible and eternal things of God, but are toſſed in the ſea of confuſion, and darkneſs and cannot reſt; conſider theſe things, are not we whom you hate and perſecure, and make a great ſtir and noiſe about, as a city ſet on a hill which cannot be hid, and unknown to you, yea verily we are, and are not we whom you grievouſly afflict without cauſe, as the light of the world, and the ſalt of the earth now, and can you endure the ſavour of them that fear the living God, and worſhip him in the ſpirit and in the truth amongſt you, are you not like the horſe that ſmells the battel afar off, and rageth when he hears the ſound of a trumpet: but the trumpet of the Lord God is ſounded out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and you ſhall tremble, and your whole foundation ſhall be ſhaken, the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <p>Come let us try you, ye that cry peace, and cry for peace, can you endure to be tryed by the light of the ſon of God, who ſeek not honour from men, but is meek and without guile, and ſaith ſwear not at all, and ſaith, I came not to ſend peace on earth but a ſword; come how do you feel his life and words, that reſpecteth not the perſon of any man, and denies the glory of the world, and teſtifieth againſt the evil thereof without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether in rulers, prieſts or people, and ſaith how can you believe that receive honour
<pb facs="tcp:45945:4"/> one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God onely, are his words peace to your life, and do you ſavour them well as a joy to you, or are they as a ſword in your bowels, and cuts you to the heart as <hi>Stephens</hi> did, when he ſpake to the Council Scribes, Prieſts and Elders, and people who gnaſhed on him with their teeth, and ſtoned him for the teſtimony of Jeſus, come try your peace whether it be in the earth, upon which the ſword is to come, or whether he is your peace that brings the ſword upon the earth, who ſeeks not honour from men, who is the condemnation of them whoſe deeds are evil. And ſee if you can endure the ſalting with fire, and the day of tryal and the hour of temptation that will come upon all them that dwell on the earth to try them, and do you not dwell on the earth, who are ſeeking earthly honour and impriſoning for it, and will not the ſword of Gods righteous judgements come upon you for theſe things, ſee how you exceed your father, who did but tempt, and not impriſon the ſon of God, when he would not bow down nor worſhip him, think on this and tremble, ye ſeed of evil doers, and conſider your vvaies and the vvhole courſe of your life, and the end thereof, and ſee if you can dvvell vvith devouring fire, and vvith the everlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, for a fire the Lord God of our life is kindling among you, and the thickets of the forreſt and the ravenous beaſts, and the falſe Prophets ſhall be conſumed by it, and the day is at hand, that a ſword ſhall be upon your right arme, and it ſhall be dryed up, and your right eye ſhall be utterly darkned, and you ſhall look for light but behold darkneſs, and dimneſs and blindneſs, and anguiſh and vexation of ſpirit, with bitter lamentation, and for a comforter, but there will be none becauſe you have deſpiſed reproof, and did not chooſe the fear of the Lord, but have ſaid in your hearts there is no God, and what Lord ſhall controle us, therefore Gods righteous witneſs (the light in your conſciences, which makes manifeſt the hidden things of diſhoneſty) will judge and condemne you for all your ungodly deeds and hard ſpeeches, that you ungodly have committed, and ſpoken againſt him and his dear children, and that is nigh you wh ch will tell the matter, and he that ſeeth in ſecret will reward you openly, according to the works of your hands, and will let you ſee all that ever you have acted, in vvhoſe living povver and life I novv vvarn you to conſider your vvaies, and repent vvhile you have yet time, and priſe this your viſitation, leſt it ſtand a dreadful vvitneſs for the Lord God againſt you, and the thing that belong to your eternal peace, be for ever hid from your eyes, and your houſe left unto you deſolate.</p>
            <p>This is a warning from the ſpirit of the living God in his ſervant, who ſuffers (in the ſpirit of meekneſs) for his precious truths ſake who deſires not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but rather that he might turn from his wickedneſs and live, and am in the houſe of correction at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> where I have freely given up my life in the will of God, if it be to the finiſhing my teſtimony againſt a ſinful and adulterous generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to which priſon I was ſent as a wanderer from the town in which I was born, (and which is in the ſame county) and have been kept neer 12. months becauſe I cannot promiſe to go home, againſt whom no evil or breach of law hath been char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, though too Aſſiſes and four Seſſions have paſt in the time of my impriſonment, who am of the world called,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Bayley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:45945:4"/>
            <head>A voice and viſitation of God to the Inhabitants of the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Lord God Almighty of heaven and earth (who is the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and of <hi>Jacob</hi>) is riſen with his eternal dreadful power, to gather and to ſcatter, and no people powers or nations ſhall be able to ſtop his way, for he in whoſe preſence all the nations of the earth, are but as a drop of a bucket, is riſen as a Giant to the battlel, and he who maketh war in righteouſneſs is gone forth conquering and to conquer, out of whoſe mouth goeth a ſharp two edged ſword, with which he will ſlay the wicked, and cut the heathen, that rage aſunder, for the Lord God of life and terrible Majeſty, is now riſen to judge for the meek of the earth, and to plead the cauſe of the poor, againſt him that is too ſtrong for him, and is now making inquiſition for blood, and he remembreth the cry of the humble, for the year of his redeemed is come, and the day of vengeance is in his heart, he proclaimeth liberty to the captives, and the opening of the priſon doors to them that are bound, who hears the groanings of his pretious ſeed, and for its ſake is come down to deliver.</p>
            <p>Therefore woe, thick darkneſs and dreadful plagues vvill come upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his hoſt, vvho oppreſſeth the righteous ſeed (the born of God) in the land of your dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and houſe of bondage; for the Prophet of the Lord God like unto <hi>Moſes</hi> (vvho ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth before man good and evil, life and death, the bleſſing and the curſe) vvhich God hath raiſed up in the midſt of his brethren vvhich all are to hear, he is novv trying <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or the ſons and daughters of men vvho are hardned, from his fear, vvho loves the darkneſs rather then the light becauſe their deeds are evill, and refuſeth to let that go vvhich groaneth, and doth ſigh and cry for deliverance, and hungers and thirſts after righteouſneſs, vvhich being deſolate and trodden under foot in many, it mourneth unto him, and the cry of it is entred into the ears of the Lord God of reſt, and this is the ſeed vvhich the Lord is gathering into his gardner, of eternal do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and peace, and all the chaffe vvhich about it oppreſſeth (though in a profeſſion without the life and power of the ſeed) will the Lord God conſume with the unquench able fire.</p>
            <p>Therefore take heed, and be you warned of the Lord God of heaven, all ye rulers, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verners and people of the earth, and all you of this iſle, and whom the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath moved many of his dear ſervants in the dreadful pure power of his might, and in the bowels of love to viſit your ſouls: I ſay take heed of ſtriving to hinder this the great mighty and powerful work of Gods love amongſt the Children of men, as you will anſwer it before the throne of God and of the Lamb, who is the light of the world, and lighteth every man that cometh into the world, to whom all judgement and power is committed, who is now come to judge the world in righteouſneſs and the people with his truth, and he muſt reign till all his enemies are brought under his feet, the Lord God of everlaſting ſtrength hath ſpoken it: for he is now coming in ten thouſands of his ſaints to convince all that are ungodly among you of their ungodly deeds, which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches, which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him, who is the true light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, who upon them will execute the judgment written, for now is the Lord of life fulfilling his promiſe, which he hath ſpoken by his former Prophets, that in the laſt dayes the mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed upon the top of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the hills, and many people ſhall flow unto it, and ſhall goe and ſay, come ye and let us go up unto the mountain of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he will teach us his waies, and we will walk in his paths, and let us walk in the light of the Lord; ſo that the head ſtone (the mountain of the Lords houſe (which the wiſe maſter-builders have rejected and refuſed, (who is the light of the world the
<pb facs="tcp:45945:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> eternal wiſdome and power of God) is he eſtabliſhing upon the top of all your dark mountains, of pride, envy and ambition, and exalting above your lofty hills of oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and rage, and his day (who is the light) ſhall be upon every one that is proud, and upon every one that is high and lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low, and the Lord God alone ſhall be exalted on that day; for the decree is gone forth, and the conſuming fire is kindled among the thickets of the forreſt, and his eternal love is ſtreaming forth toward the meek in the earth, and againſt this his mighty and powerful work, the gates of hell, and all the ru lars of the darkneſs of this world, ſhall never prevail, the eternal Lord God of heaven and earth hath ſpoken it, Therefore in vain do all the potſheards of the earth ſtrive vvith their maker, and they that reſiſteth, reſiſteth not man, but God, (who is the higher power that lighteth every man that cometh into the world) and ſuch receives to themſelves damnation, for to him we are ſubject who rides meekly upon the foal of an aſs, the wild aſſes colt, (he that readeth let him underſtand) and he is our peace, in whoſe mouth is found no guile, therefore let none be high minded but fear; for thou ô man (who art lifted up above the Stem of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> and the off-ſpring of <hi>David,</hi>) beareſt not the root but the root thee, therefore thou art to fear and dread the preſence of the living God, and depart from evil, and this is the beginning of the eternal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (which is juſtified of her children) which is from above, pure, peaceable meek, gentle ſober, and eaſie to be intreated, whoſe voice is to you (in the power of its love) ye people of this Iſland, and this will lead you if you embrace it, into its own paths which is eternal peace, and this leads out of raſhneſs, crookedneſs and perverſneſs, and out of headineſs and high mindedneſs, and out of all the luſts and pleaſures of ſin, which are but for a ſeaſon, and this brings to be juſt merciful and tender hearted, and to ſpeak truth every man to his neighbour, and this will lead to entertain ſtrangers, when by it you come to ſee your ſelves have been ſtrangers to the life of God, (which is holy juſt and righteous and full of good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and this will let you ſoldiers ſee that you ought not to do violence, or accuſe any man falſly, and that you ought to live ſoberly and righteouſly in this preſent world: for all men ſhall know that the Captain of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (vvhich vvas made perfect through ſufferings, vvho is the true light that is gone forth conquering and to conquer vvith his eternal arme of povver) that he is King of Kings and Lord of Lords, and muſt reign over the world, and all its enmity and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty povvers of darkneſs, (vvhich is but as a vapour) for by him the vvorld vvas made, and he is the heir that is novv come to take peace from the earth, and to call and gather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Vineyard of eternal life, and thoſe that are vvilling and obedient ſhall eat the good of the land, but thoſe that refuſe and rebel ſhall be devoured vvith his ſvvord, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>This of the Lord of life vvas I moved in this Iſland to ſpeak forth as a viſitation and vvarning from him, unto you the inhabitants thereof, both governernours, ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, prieſts and people, <date>on the 8th. of the 11th. month, 58.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By me vvho am a ſervant of the living God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> called <hi>Will. Bayly.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed <hi>3.</hi> month <hi>4</hi> day for M. W.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45945:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
